Performance Baselines and the Standard Deviation
Welcome back to our session on quality baseline.
Where we had previously looked at variation
in a set of data, like measurement of the length of these lines.
To compute a standard deviation, which is kind of like an inch or a pound.
It tells us the standard amount by which a measurement in here
would deviate from its expected value.
Of course we're not going to get into the specifics of that right now.
Then we took that example we went over and  looked at IQ.
Ultimately to a process forming a histogram.
Now, what I want to do is come back to this notion of a normal distribution.
So, here's some performance characteristic that we'll call Y.
And its balance point right here, is the average.
I’m just going to let that be AVG for average for right now
because this is such a cursory overview of what we’re doing.
I’m now go to pick a point out here on Y.
Let's say that this is IQ. Remember, that it was 100.
And remember, over here I’m going to pick a point. Now, I’m going to say an IQ of 120.
Now by taking all the IQ measurements in computing the standard deviation,
which we designate by the symbol σ.
Let's recognize that σ is a function of variation
that is out there.
I’m not going to get into the specifics of how to compute the standard deviation.
Let's just represent, that it's a computed number
and let's suppose that we compute it to be 10.
What this would say is that the distance between 100 and 120.
That distance. 10 and 10.
Or 120-100 is 20.
So, there's 10, 20. That is 2 σ.
Two standard deviations. So, we compute for the range of variation that we see.
The standard deviation. For the range of variation. In this case, it was 10.
And now we discover, given the magnitude of that. That there are 2
standard deviations from 100 to 120.
Now, statisticians have already made the association
between numbers of standard deviations
and how much area is under this curve, beyond that point we're interested in.
So, what we want to do is to consult what's called a table
of area under the normal curve. A table of area under the normal curve.
And it will tell us how much area
is beyond 120.
That's the probability of getting a person with an IQ
greater than 120. By the area under the curve, because we know 100%
of the area under this curve is between a minimum IQ
and out here near infinite IQ. So 100% of IQ’s
fit under the area of the normal curve. So, if I look at the average.
And I happen to know that 50%
of the total area under this curve is between the average and here. 50% is over here.
So, if I know this amount of area,
then by subtraction I can find this tail area.
And that's what a table of area under the normal curve helps us do.
Now let's just suppose, for the sake of argument,
that we define that tale area as a probability or as p.
Thus, we would know, that for some σ,
Kσ is equivalent to a certain probability.
We will come back and revisit this idea.
Thank you for choosing SSMI.